It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
If you look inside your mouth
and you find lacy white patches,
sometimes with redness or sores,
on the inside of the
cheeks, tongue, or gums,
you may have the inflammatory
condition oral lichen planus.
Here is one way to treat it.
There's an inflammatory
autoimmune condition
known as oral lichen planus,
in which our immune system starts
attacking the lining of our mouth.
This is what it looks like.
It's actually not that rare,
it strikes up to five percent
of the population,
particularly women,
and about one percent of cases
can turn into cancer.
There's no cure,
there's just
symptomatic treatments:
steroids, immunosuppressants,
and total glucosides of peony.
Like, peony peony?
Yes, medicinal properties in the
root of the common garden peony.
That's neat.
But are there any edible plants
that may help?
There's a plant called purslane,
one of the most common weeds
in the world—
you can see it growing out
of the cracks in the sidewalk
everywhere you look,
once you start looking.
Its healing properties
were thought to be so reliable
that Roman savant
Pliny the Elder
advised wearing the plant
as an amulet to expel all evil.
I don't know about that.
What about just eating it?
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
found that 83 percent
of those in the purslane group
experienced partial or complete
clinical improvement,
compared to 83 percent
in the placebo group
who either didn't respond
or got worse.
So, this simple weed appears
to be clinically effective
in the treatment
of oral lichen planus,
with no side effects.
In a comparison
to the efficacy and safety
of nine different treatments,
including steroids
and immunosuppressants,
purslane appeared to not only
be the safest,
but the most effective
treatment available,
with only good side-effects:
lowering triglycerides
and decreasing inflammation.
You can overdo it, though.
Purslane is a high oxalate green,
with nearly half as much
oxalates as spinach.
So, even if you don't
tend to get kidney stones,
you don't want to eat four pounds
(2 kg) of purslane at a time.
I know it's delicious,
but as little as a pound and a half
(0.70 kg) at a time,
or even two pounds (0.90 kg)
spread out over two meals
could potentially overload
the kidney and cause damage.
Purslane can even fight
lichen planus topically.
A purslane gel appeared to work
as well as topical steroids,
the gold standard treatment.
The researchers concluded that
purslane is a "magical" herb:
beneficial,
lacking side effects,
and therefore can be
a safer alternative drug
in oral lichen planus treatment.
But by alternative "drug"
they're just talking about a weed
that grows for free all over.
In our next story,
we look at additional ways
to treat lichen planus.
Lichen planus is a chronic
autoimmune disease,
typically of our moist membranes,
such as the inside of our mouth,
but can also affect other body surfaces.
Current treatments are not curative
but rather palliative,
aimed at relieving pain.
We’ve tried steroids, antibiotics,
chemotherapy, and surgery,
and none appear to be
particularly effective.
So, even for palliative pain relief,
we don’t have great options;
that’s why case reports
like this are so exciting.
After drinking 2 ounces
of aloe vera juice a day
and applying aloe topically as well.
But, is ingested oral aloe
vera a potion or poison?
Internal use of aloe may cause
acute hepatitis—liver inflammation,
as well as electrolyte imbalances,
and you should definitely not inject aloe.
But oral use is also not
recommended either.
This is primarily because of case reports
of aloe-induced hepatitis.
Aloe is, ironically, presented
as a detoxifying product
but can actually end
up causing liver damage.
How do we know it was the aloe, though?
The assessment of suspected
herbal-induced liver injury
is challenging, because
there’s hundreds of things
out there that can damage your liver.
Here’s the kind of checklist
you have to go through as a doctor
to rule out other causes before
you blame it on the plant.
Do you have some kind of viral hepatitis,
or other kind of liver infection,
or it could be various drugs
or toxins and diseases.
So, maybe it was one
of these other things,
and it was just a coincidence
that the problem started
after drinking aloe.
The gold standard, in terms of trying
to prove cause-and-effect, is
a positive re-exposure test—
that’s how you can diagnose
drug-induced liver injury.
Liver inflammation disappears
when you remove the drug,
and then reappears when
you add the drug back,
which is rarely done,
for obvious reasons.
Well, has there ever been
a re-challenge case published for aloe?
Yes.
Aloe-induced toxic
hepatitis that shot up again
after stopping then
restarting aloe ingestion.
Aloe consumption has also been
linked to thyroid dysfunction.
A woman with lichen
planus started swallowing
2 teaspoons of aloe vera juice a day.
She started feeling unjustifiably tired.
Labwork showed her
thyroid function was low,
but she perked right back
up after stopping the aloe,
and her thyroid function
returned to normal.
What if, instead of swallowing, though,
she just swished the
aloe around in her mouth
to try to help the lichen planus
and then spit it out?
We didn’t know...
until it was put to the test.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial:
54 patients randomized to
a topical aloe vera gel
or placebo gel for 8 weeks.
81% in the aloe group got better
compared to just 4% in the placebo group.
Furthermore, two patients
treated with aloe
had a complete clinical remission.
That’s rare.
It’s considered a chronic condition;
yet, a few weeks applying aloe,
and the nasty erosive
lesions disappeared.
How about compared to a
steroid ointment, though?
Topical aloe vera gel was superior—
more effective than the steroids,
a significant difference
appearing within 2 weeks.
So, although corticosteroids are
still considered the gold standard,
aloe vera shows promising results,
especially with no adverse effects,
when applied topically,
compared to various adverse
side effects of the corticosteroids.
That’s for oral lichen planus, though.
What about the efficacy of aloe vera gel
in the treatment of lichen
planus of the genitals?
Lichen planus of the
vulva is quite common,
affecting 1-2% of the population,
and it may be even harder to treat.
There are flares and partial remission
but no tendency for complete remission.
And, indeed, that’s what they
saw in the placebo group.
One woman had a good response,
but most had little or no response,
but applying aloe vera gel instead,
and 9 out of 10 responded,
and one woman had a
complete clinical remission.
They conclude that aloe vera gel
is a safe and effective treatment.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.